Finding Aid for News and Information Services (University of Michigan) Audiovisual Materials
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
- Digital Video
  - News Briefs, 2007-2012
    - 1,000 Pitches 2008, .mov file; The 1,000 Pitches business plan competition gathered 1,044 pitches from students across campus, demonstrating that even in this economy, good ideas are proliferating. An entrepreneurship competition. Video interview with the president of a student group that led the organization of an entrepreneurship competition.
    - A new renewable energy concept 2008, .mov file; A device called VIVACE developed at the University of Michigan draws power out of slow water currents to produce clean electricity. It imitates the swim strategy of a school of fish. VIVACE harnesses vibrations in slow moving water currents Video interview with professor, animations.
    - A universal language 2008, .mov file; Michigan Gospel Chorale is going along with U-M President Coleman on trip to Africa U-M students aim to connect through song with Ghana audiences A video of the Michigan Gospel Chorale, including interviews with members along with rehearsal and performance footage.
    - An eclectic exhibit 2008, .mov file; The exhibit features the most current works of U-M's art school faculty U-M annual faculty show diverse showcase of talent. Video looks at annual art faculty exhibition.
    - Ballast-free ship 2008, .mov file; The U-M ballast-free ship concept eliminates ballast tanks, compartments where foreign organisms can stow away. U-M invention could block aquatic invaders. Video showing tests of U-M ballast free ship, along with interviews of profs + extras.
    - Big 10 poll: Obama widens lead 2008, .mov file; University of Michigan communications studies Professor Michael Traugott fields U-M students' questions related to the second Big Ten Battleground Poll on this year's presidential election. Michigan voters also indicate concern about economy Audio interview w/Michael Traugott.
    - Big Ten battleground poll 2008, .mov file; University of Michigan communications studies Professor Michael Traugott fields U-M students' questions that were answered in the first Big Ten Battleground Poll on this year's presidential election. Some findings of the first poll of its kind in eight Big Ten Students pose questions on the presidential election, answered by results of a poll in eight of the Big Ten states.
    - Blazar in action 2008, .mp4 file; Blazars, among the most energetic objects in the universe, are fueled by super massive black holes at the core of certain giant elliptical galaxies. Periodically, they emit jets of high-energy plasma at almost the speed of light. Jets of high-energy plasma are caused by the black hole at the center of blazars. An animation of a blazar at the center of a galaxy emitting jets of high-energy plasma.
    - Charitable giving 2008, .mov file; Americans appear to be consistent in their giving, and don't stop giving during recessions. Recession does not stop donations to non-profits agencies Audio interview w/assistant professor H. Luke Shaefer.
    - Chinese autos are coming 2008, .mov file; Detroit International Auto Show prompts U-M auto expert Bruce Belzowski Detroit International Auto Show to speculate on Chinese auto imports to the U.S.
    - Desmond Tutu Lecture 2008, .mov file; Anti-Apartheid leader Archbishop Desmond Tutu spoke about forgiveness and the imperative to help others when he delivered the Raoul Wallenberg Lecture at the University of Michigan, October 29, 2008.
    - Direct meaning 2008, .mov file; The director, Mbala Nkanga, gives a brief interpretation of the play, Madmen and Specialists. Understanding Theatre Department's opening play. This is a video interview with Nkanga.
    - Future forest 2008, .mov file; Glimpsing future forests by removing thousands of trees Glimpsing future forests by removing thousands of trees Glimpsing future forests by removing thousands of trees.
    - Global warming issues are important to Michigan residents 2008, .mov file; A new U-M asks Michigan residents about global warming issues and climate policy options. Three out of four Michigan residents would open their wallets if it increased renewable energy production. They would pay more than $50 annually for renewable energy production A news podcast with Barry Rabe, professor of public policy.
    - Going green: Detroit's auto show 2008, .mov file; Detroit International Auto Show is less red, white and blue and more green this year. U-M auto expert sums up the 2008 North American International Auto Show video interview with UMTRI's Bruce Belzowski about automakers going green, and the future of the Chinese auto industry.
    - Graduate exhibit filled with powerful works 2008, .mp4 file; A first-hand look at how artists prepared for annual exhibit and the various venues for the show. Arts seniors leave mark. A video featuring interview with graduating seniors from Art and Design and overview of IP exhibit.
    - Growing old with style 2008, .mov file; The range of works challenges conventional notions of aging Exhibit inspired by theme of aging Exhibit curator Bill Burkhardt offers a tour of the show.
    - House of dreams 2008, .mp4 file; Joe Trumpey is building a straw bale house, an ecologically efficient dwelling. The house stands as a testament to self-reliance. U-M prof blends art and ethics In the video, Trumpey explains the many details that go into building the house, and his reason for pursuing the project in Grass Lake.
    - Large turnout by women voters 2008, .mp4 file; Clinton, McCain victories shake up election.
    - Michigan to Mercury 2008, .mov file; The Fast Imaging Plasma Spectrometer is a space instrument built at the University of Michigan. Here's the story of its journey to Mercury on board the MESSENGER spacecraft. U-M space instrument arrives on MESSENGER Video interview of Associate Professor Thomas Zurbuchen, project leader of the Fast Imaging Plasma Spectrometer space instrument on board NASA's MESSENGER spacecraft.
    - New age of publishing 2008, .mov file; U-M's Shapiro Library is the first university library to install innovative book-making machine U-M at vanguard printing on-demand books. A close-up look at the Espresso Book Machine, which prints books from U-M digitized collection.
    - New LSI philanthropic fund 2008, .mov file; The Innovation Partnership is a new fund that will help guide LSI discoveries from the lab bench to the marketplace. LSI launches unique new research fund Life Sciences Institute Director Alan Saltiel discusses LSI's new Innovation Partnership.
    - Race and identity 2008, .mov file; U-M professor Ed West offers insight into how being raised bi-racial can broaden understanding of cultural differences, an especially timely discussion in the weeks leading up to the presidential election. U-M prof searches for meaning of race in cultural contexts First-person essay from U-M Prof Ed West. He discusses growing up bi-racial in a black and white America.
    - Social impact of rising prison population 2008, .mov file; In late Feb, the Pew Center published a report that documents increasing prison population. Among the startling results: About 1 in 99 Americans are in prison, and the U.S. incarcerates more people than any other nation. The two profs explore the need to elevate the topic of prison reform in the national discourse. U-M profs explore effect on communities, families A video of a trenchant, compelling conversation between Buzz Alexander, founder of annual prison art exhibit, and Jeff Morenoff, researcher at Institute for Social Research.
    - The Economy 2008, .mov file; U-M Economist Richard Curtin, who directs the Reuters/University of Michigan Surveys of Consumers, provides insight on what lies ahead for consumers. Consumer Outlook for 2009 Video interview with economist Richard Curtin.
    - The Flying Fish robotic seaplane 2008, .mov file; Named after its inspiration, the Flying Fish is believed to be the first autonomous seaplane. It has a 7-foot wingspan and is just larger than a pelican. This craft can take off and land on water by itself. A video interview with two U-M professors who helped develop the craft and footage of sea trials.
    - The future of libraries 2008, .mov file; The Digital Age is changing the game for libraries, which are finding themselves providing an increasing number of information technology services. Meeting challenges in the Internet era. Video interview with professor and student.
    - The psychology of giving 2008, .mov file; Caring for an ailing spouse may prolong your life, according to a new study that provides fresh evidence that giving to those we love can bring us better health and longer lives. Giving really is better than receiving. Video interview.
    - U-M and Pfizer 2008, .mov file; Comments from a news conference outlining the University of Michigan's purchase of Pfizer's former Ann Arbor property U-M to buy Pfizer's former Ann Arbor property News conference outlining the University of Michigan's purchase of Pfizer's former Ann Arbor property.
    - UM Biological Station at 100 2008, .mov file; Celebrating its 100th session this summer, U-M's campus in the north woods is a very different place than it was at its inception, but its mission of combining research and education, with a focus on crucial environmental issues, is unchanged. Campus in the woods celebrates centennial Then-and-now still photos, video interviews with UMBS faculty.
    - University of Michigan Avoiding hip fractures 2008, .mp4 file; A demonstration of the parachutist's landing style, considered the safest way to land a sideways fall from a standing position.
    - University of Michigan Blazar in action 2008, .mp4 file; Blazars, among the most energetic objects in the universe, are fueled by super massive black holes at the core of certain giant elliptical galaxies. Periodically, they emit jets of high-energy plasma at almost the speed of light.
    - University of Michigan Uninsured figures on the rise 2008, .mp4 file; Helen Levy talks about why more Americans don't have health coverage.
    - A low-cost surgical lamp 2009, .mov file; Engineering students have developed a low-cost, battery-powered surgical lamp to be used in developing nations where electricity isn't reliable. Earlier this month, the members of Michigan Health Engineered for All Lives, or M-HEAL, sent their prototype lamp to Uganda where it will undergo testing. Students created a surgical lamp for developing nations. Video interview with students.
    - A new graduation tradition 2009, .mov file; In recent years, at the University of Michigan, a new tradition has taken root. Many students who attend the customary Spring Commencement are also taking part in more personal celebrations. Graduation Celebrations at the University of Michigan The video captures minority graduation celebrations across the campus.
    - A new lease on life 2009, .mov file; U-M students talk about why they participate in the Michigan Prisoner Re-entry program, which provides counseling and services to former inmates. U-M students help ex-offenders adjust to society. Slideshow project with U-M students.
    - America's changing families 2009, .mov file; Since 1968, the ISR Panel Study of Income Dynamics has been following different generations of the same families to learn how their lives have changes A close-up on the ISR Panel Study of Income Dynamic. Interviews with researchers and interviewers, and selected study findings.
    - Ancient mammal fossil finds 2009, .mov file; A limestone counter top and a practiced eye played roles in the discovery of a trove of fossils that may shed light on the origins of African wildlife. Limestone counter top leads to ancient mammal fossil finds Segment from "Wild Chronicles" TV program.
    - Assuring Michigan's Workforce 2009, .mov file; The University of Michigan College of Engineering is organizing the Diversity Summit to discuss how Michigan universities can create engineers who are better prepared to face the global challenges of the 21st century. Summit on Diversity + Opportunity in K16 + Engineering Edu Interviews with Dean, Associate Dean of College of Engineering.
    - Autism awareness 2009, .mov file; U-M autism expert Catherine Lord is nationally known and sought after for her input on this growing epidemic. Helping children Video on U-M's autism clinic.
    - Automakers and the Feds 2009, .mp4 file; New vehicles should please the auto industry's newest stakeholder---the federal government. Video interview with Bruce Belzowski.
    - Bendable self-healing concrete 2009, .mov file; Watch professor Victor Li's bendable self-healing concrete in action. A researcher shows how this material compares with regular concrete. A demonstration of concrete that bends. Video interview with a researcher.
    - Bracing for earthquakes 2009, .mov file; Engineers at the University of Michigan simulated an off-the-charts earthquake in a laboratory in December to test the strength of their new technique for bracing high-rise buildings. A better way to brace buildings in seismic zones Video interview of professors and doctoral student with footage of earthquake simulation.
    - Brain health 2009, .mov file; A study of nearly 14,000 U.S. and English seniors shows that 75-year-olds in the U.S. have memories as good, on average, as 65-year-olds in England. U.S. seniors news video with professor Kenneth Langa.
    - Building a proud legacy 2009, .mov file; Since the mid 1980s, U-M grads have made a mark on Broadway productions, and serve as ambassadors for a program considered among the tops in the nation Musical Theatre celebrates 25th anniversary. A look at the impact and mission of U-M Musical Theatre Department on American musical theater.
    - Camp Davis yesterday and today 2009, .mov file; Established on an abandoned ranch in 1929, U-M's Camp Davis Rocky Mountain Field Station has provided a close-knit learning community in a breathtaking outdoor setting for generations of students. This year the camp celebrates its 80th anniversary with the opening of a block of new cabins. U-M's field station in Rockies celebrates 80th anniversary. Narrated slide show with video clips of scenery and students working in the field.
    - Can you find a cure? 2009, .mov file; Pete Dingeman recently visited University of Michigan researchers whose work he helps support. Researchers come face to face with patient video interview with Sean Morrison, Pete Dingeman and Johanna Buchstaller.
    - Celebrating a century of dance 2009, .mov file; An overview of the 100-year history of dance at U-M dates back before department was established and includes some surprises. U-M's dance teaching dates among longest in nation Jessica Fogel, professor of dance, explains how U-M's legacy inspires the mission of the dance department.
    - Cells as classroom computers 2009, .mp4 file; Professor Elliot Soloway has developed software for cell phones that allows them to be used in classrooms, giving each student his own computer. He says this could revolutionize education. Cell phones could give each student his own computer Video interview with professor and demonstration of how his software works.
    - Challenged kids on bikes 2009, .mov file; Children and young adults with Down syndrome and autism learn to ride bikes in about a week at the University of Michigan bike camp. Autistic, Down syndrome kids see milestone at U-M bike camp. This is a video of interviews with faculty and parents and children with autism and Down syndrome participating in the U-M bike camp.
    - Challenges in education system 2009, .mov file; University of Michigan Professor Brian Rowan discusses some of the challenges facing the education system. Cuts, consolidation; pressures school districts face Interview with Professor Brian Rowan.
    - City Club of Cleveland 2009, .mov file; University of Michigan President Mary Sue Coleman speaks on The Role of Research Universities in Transforming the Midwest Economy before the City Club of Cleveland.
    - Clean energy entrepreneurship 2009, .mov file; Student finalists for the Clean Energy Prize talk about their ideas for businesses that could help save the planet, and how this contest and other University resources have helped them advance their innovations. Finalists for the Clean Energy Prize discuss their projects. Video interview with 6 students.
    - Cleaner cooking in Nicaragua 2009, .mov file; University of Michigan students traveled to Nicaragua last summer to learn about and install a biodigester, which will provide cleaner cooking fuel. A Michigan Engineering student project. Video interviews with students and professor Steve Skerlos, plus footage of the students working in Nicaragua.
    - Coming home 2009, .mov file; U-M Musical Theatre Chair Brent Wagner talks about featured performances in upcoming 25th anniversary concert More than 50 alumni to perform in anniversary concert. A brief description of the excitement mounting for concert.
    - Complex health care system 2009, .mov file; University of Michigan School of Public Health professor discusses universal health care and other issues. Issues include universal care, physician shortage. Interview with professor Richard Lichtenstein
    - Decoding public health reforms 2009, .mp4 file; Earlier in the debate, University of Michigan School of Public Health professor discussed some of the complexities of the proposed health care reforms. Interview with Professor Paula Lantz.
    - Detecting suicide bombers 2009, .mov file; Engineering undergraduates developed a wireless network of portable, hand-held sensors that could be hidden around an environment to detect improvised explosive devices, weapons often used by suicide bombers. Engineering students develop new technology Video interviews with students and professor Nilton Renno.
    - Encouraging economic growth 2009, .mov file; Michael Finney, president and CEO of Ann Arbor SPARK, testifies before the Michigan Senate Education Subcommittee about the ways U-M helps encourage regional economic growth. U-M role in promoting economic transformation Michael Finney, president and CEO of Ann Arbor SPARK, testifies before the Michigan Senate Education Subcommittee about the ways U-M helps encourage regional economic growth.
    - Family dynamic suffers 2009, .mov file; University of Michigan professor discusses how recession is affecting families and children on different levels. Family gatherings can help keep people together during tough times. Impact of recession on families and children Interview with professor Pamela Smock.
    - Fatal (fiscal) attraction 2009, .mov file; When it comes to choosing a spouse, tightwads tend to marry spendthrifts, confirming the adage, opposites attract. Spendthrifts and tightwads in marriage. News interview with assistant professor Scott Rick.
    - Fight song moves droplets 2009, .mov file; This video provided by College of Engineering researchers uses the Michigan fight song to demonstrate how sound waves can be used to move droplets through microfluidic devices. A new microfluidic device uses music to propel droplets. Demonstration video provided by researchers.
    - Finding the missing carbon 2009, .mov file; Professor Anna Michalak is working to solve the mystery of the missing carbon. She uses sophisticated mathematical tools to help predict future climate change. Predicting climate change. Video interview with Anna Michalak.
    - Flu: Prepare, don't panic 2009, .mov file; What is a pandemic, how do we prepare but not panic, what does swine flu mean to us? All flu not created equal, what is swine flu? Video discussion with professor Allison Aiello.
    - Global health design at U-M 2009, .mov file; As part of the University of Michigan College of Engineering's new Global Health Design program, students designed and built portable pelvic exam tables for use in Ghana. Students develop medical solutions abroad. Video interviews with students and professors involved in the Global Health Design project at the University of Michigan College of Engineering.
    - Global Health issues 2009, .mov file; Sandro Galea discusses the goals for the new U-M Center for Global Health, and why we should care about global health. Galea discusses global health issues. Video of Sandro Galea discussing the new U-M Center for Global Health.
    - Great Lakes in transition 2009, .mov file; University of Michigan scientists spend two days on Lake Michigan, studying the wide-ranging effects of invasive mussels. University of Michigan scientists study the Great Lakes Lake Michigan trip, interviews.
    - Growing old in Lebanon 2009, .mov file; University of Michigan and Eastern Michigan University researcher Kristine Ajrouch is studying social relationships in her grandparents' homeland of Lebanon. Researcher Kristine Ajrouch studies Lebanese society Narrative by Ajrouch about her studies of Lebanese society.
    - Health care reform 2009, .mov file; University of Michigan School of Public Health professor discusses whether health reform will simply cover more people, or also lower costs and increase efficiency. Can reform achieve low cost, efficient health care? Video interview with Dean Smith.
    - Helping children succeed 2009, .mov file; New research shows that parents who want to help their children succeed in school may need to go back to school themselves. Parents should educate themselves to help kids succeed. Video interview with professor Pamela Davis-Kean.
    - Hope for the holidays 2009, .mov file; University of Michigan professor Christopher Peterson talks about benefits of positive psychology during the holiday season. Interview with Christopher Peterson.
    - Hosting a major sport event 2009, .mov file; Professor Rodney Fort in the School of Kinesiology talks about the real economic considerations to account for before agreeing to host a major sports event More than money matters when hosting mega-sporting events. Video interview of professor Rodney Fort.
    - Huron River performance 2009, .mov file; This intricately layered performance piece interweaves live and recorded music, dance, video and poetry. 'Mapping the River' performance melds science and art. This is a video with three faculty interviews.
    - Innovation economy partnership 2009, .mp4 file; V.P. for Research Stephen Forrest talks about U-M's commitment to transforming the economy of Michigan Transforming Michigan's economy V.P. for Research Stephen Forrest talks about U-M's commitment to transforming the economy of Michigan.
    - iPhone as musical instrument 2009, .mov file; Students at the University of Michigan are building musical instruments for iPhones in a first-of-its kind class. A class and concert at the University of Michigan Video interview with professor Georg Essl; interviews with students in the class; demonstration of musical instruments on iPhone.
    - Larry Page Address 2009, .mov file; Google Co-founder and President for Products Larry Page was main speaker at the University of Michigan 2009 Spring Commencement.
    - Latin Tinge 2009, .mov file; This class, taught by Jesse Hoffnung-Garskof, delves into Latin American history and culture through its musical creations, including the tango, mambo, salsa and more. Class gives students insights into Latin music and history One in the series Life Lessons---University of Michigan classes that change your world.